A Guide to the Cumming Family Papers
University of Virginia Library
- SUBGROUP I: Booth Family Papers
  - Series I. Correspondence and Legal Papers
    - Correspondence and Papers of Rebecca Hicks Booth and the Hicks family, 1830-1864 (Box Box 1)
    - Correspondence of Robert H. Booth and family, 1843-1860 (Box Box 1)
    - Correspondence of Edwin Gilliam Booth, 1846-1881 (Box Box 1)
    - Dr. Edwin Gilliam Booth to Edwin Gilliam Booth, 1861-1869 (Box Box 1)
    - Correspondence of Clara Haxell (Thomson) Booth and the Thomson Family, 1858-1922 (Box Box 1)
    - Letters from Archer Jones Booth, 1862-1864 (Box Box 1)
    - Correspondence of Frances Rebecca Booth, 1863-1864 (Box Box 1)
    - Correspondence of Dr. Edwin Gilliam Booth, 1863-1904 (Box Box 1)
    - Correspondence between Lucy Booth and Dr. Edwin Gilliam Booth, 1890-1895 (Box Box 1)
    - Letters to Lucy Booth, 1892-1896 (Box Box 1)
    - Correspondence between Lucy Booth and Hugh Smith Cumming, 1896 (Box Box 1)
    - Surveys of land owned by the Gilliam Booth family, 1814-1843 (Box Box 1)
    - Legal Papers of the Booth family, 1817-1869 (Box Box 1)
  - Series II. Genealogical Papers
    - Armistead family, n.d. (Box Box 1)
    - Booth family, 1885-1923, n.d. (Box Box 1)
    - Booth family: Correspondence of Hugh Smith Cumming, Jr. regarding genealogical information, 1937-1965, 1978 (Box Box 1)
    - Booth family: Miscellaneous notes and related papers, including copies of family letters and documents, 1868-1963, n.d. (Box Box 1)
    - Booth and Thomson and allied families, kept in "Black Book" (Box Box 1)
    - Booth- Thomson- Throckmorton and allied families, 1929-1938 (Box Box 1)
    - Gilliam- Rootes- Bernard and allied families, 1927-1928 (Box Box 2)
    - "Record of Terry and Allied Families of Virginia and North Carolina, " compiled from notes collected by Annie Terry for Rebecca Sealy Terry White, 1934 (Box Box 2)
    - Terry family, 1907-1954 (Box Box 2)
    - Thomson family, 1919-1930, n.d. (Box Box 2)
  - Series III. Photographs and Printed Material
    - Photographs of Edwin Gilliam and Sarah Tanner (Jones) Booth and their offspring, and others, [ca. 1850-1878] (Box Box 2)
    - Photographs of " Shenstone" and " Carter's Grove, " homes of the Booth family, and of family gravesite, at St. Mary's Episcopal Church, 1963, n.d. (Box Box 2)
    - Printed material re Dr. Edwin Gilliam Booth, 1922-1956 (Box Box 2)
- SUBGROUP II: PAPERS OF DR. AND MRS. HUGH SMITH CUMMING, SR.
  - Series I. Correspondence
    - Letters to Hugh S. and Lucy B. Cumming, Sr. re birth of Lucy Cumming, 1897 (Box Box 3)
    - Letters to Lucy B. Cumming from her parents, Mr. and Mrs. E. G. Booth, 1897-1923 (Box Box 3)
    - Letters to Hugh S. and Lucy B. Cumming, Sr. re death of Lucy Cumming, 1898 (Box Box 3)
    - Letters from Hugh S. Cumming to Dr. and Mrs. E. G. Booth, 1898-1913 (Box Box 3)
    - Letters of Lucy B. Cumming to her sister Henrietta Wise, 1898-1920 (Box Box 3)
    - Correspondence between Hugh S. and Lucy B. Cumming, 1898-1941 (Box Box 3)
    - Letters to Hugh S. and Lucy B. Cumming, Sr. re birth of Hugh Smith Cumming, Jr., 1900 (Box Box 3)
    - Letters of Hugh S. Cumming, Sr. to his wife, Lucy B. Cumming, 1900-1915 (Box Box 3)
    - Letters of Hugh S. Cumming Sr. to his wife, Lucy B. Cumming, 1918 Dec-1919 Mar (Box Box 3)
    - Letters of Hugh S. Cumming, Sr. to his wife, Lucy B. Cumming, 1919 Apr-Dec (Box Box 4)
    - Letters of Hugh S. Cumming, Sr. to his wife, Lucy B. Cumming, 1920 and 1929-1938 (Box Box 4)
    - Letters of Lucy Booth Cumming to her mother, Mrs. E. G. Booth, 1901-[1924] (Box Box 4)
    - Miscellaneous Correspondence of Hugh S. and Lucy B. Cumming, 1901-1956 (Box Box 4)
    - Letters to Lucy Booth Cumming, 1903-1943 (Box Box 4)
    - Letters from Dr. and Mrs. Hugh S. Cumming, Sr. to Hugh S. Cumming, Jr., 1946-1920 (Box Box 4)
    - Letters from Dr. and Mrs. Hugh S. Cumming to Hugh S. Cumming, Jr., 1932-1936 (Box Box 4)
    - Letters from Dr. and Mrs. Hugh S. Cumming, Sr. to Hugh and Winifred Cumming, Jr., 1937-1949 (Box Box 4)
    - Correspondence of Hugh Smith Cumming, Sr. re Cumming Genealogy, 1927-1929 (Box Box 5)
    - (Copies) Letters from Franklin D. Roosevelt and H. Morganthou, Jr. to Hugh S. Cumming, Sr. re his retirement, 1936 (Box Box 5)
    - Letter of Herbert Hoover to Lucy B. Cumming, with a copy of Hoover's homecoming address, "The Meaning of America", 1948 (Box Box 5)
    - Correspondence re the publication of Hugh S. Cumming, Sr.'s Memoirs, 1948-1949 (Box Box 5)
    - Letters of Winifred Cumming to Lucy B. Cumming, 1948-1956 (Box Box 5)
  - Series II. Memoirs
    - Memoirs of General Hugh Smith Cumming, Sr., [ca. 1948] (Box Box 5)
    - Memoirs of General Hugh Smith Cumming, Sr., [ca. 1948] (Box Box 5)
    - Memoirs of General Hugh Smith Cumming, Sr., [ca. 1948] (Box Box 5)
    - Memoirs of General Hugh Smith Cumming, Sr., [ca. 1948] (Box Box 5)
    - Memoirs of General Hugh Smith Cumming, Sr., [ca. 1948] (Box Box 5)
    - Memoirs of General Hugh Smith Cumming, Sr., [ca. 1948] (Box Box 6)
    - Memoirs of General Hugh Smith Cumming, Sr., [ca. 1948] (Box Box 6)
    - Memoirs of General Hugh Smith Cumming, Sr., [ca. 1948] (Box Box 6)
    - Memoir of Lucy Booth Cumming, 1952 (Box Box 6)
    - Typescript Chapters re Surgeon General Rupert Blue and Hugh Smith Cumming, Sr.[probably from A Profile of the U. S. Public Health Service 1798-1848 by Bess Furman] (Box Box 6)
  - Series III. Miscellaneous Papers
    - Essays by Lucy Booth Cumming, 1953 and n.d. (Box Box 6)
    - Invitations issued to Dr. and Mrs. Hugh S. Cumming, 1924-1935 (Box Box 7)
    - Legal Papers, 1919 June 19 (Box Box 7)
    - Miscellaneous Papers, n.d. (Box Box 7)
    - Photographs, 1897-1934 (Box Box 7)
    - Printed Materials, 1906-1947 (Box Box 7)
    - Speeches of Dr. Hugh S. Cumming, Sr., 1924 and n.d. (Box Box 7)
  - Series IV. Bound Volumes
    - Dairy of Lucy Booth Cumming, 1922-1923, 1) (Box Box 7)
    - Date Book of Lucy Booth Cumming, 1925, 2) (Box Box 7)
    - Pictorial Record of the Medical Conference held at Cannes, France April 1-11, 1919 at the invitation of the Committee of Red Cross Societies, 3) (Box Box 7)
  - Series V. Oversize
    - Scrapbook of Hugh S. Cumming, Sr., 1892-1948, containing academic diplomas, official certificates, honorary degrees, appointments, photographs, newsclipping, obituaries, etc., 1)
    - United Daughter of the Confederacy membership certificate belonging to Lucy Booth Cumming, 2)
    - Charcoal and chalk profile sketch of Hugh S. Cumming, Sr. signed "Kinito Pon's", 3)
- SUBGROUP III: PAPERS OF AMBASSADOR HUGH SMITH CUMMING, JR.
  - Series I. Correspondence
    - A: General
      - Correspondence of Hugh Smith Cumming, 1907, 1915-1922, 1926 (Box Box 7)
      - Correspondence of Hugh Smith Cumming, 1931-1934 (Box Box 7)
      - Correspondence of Hugh Smith Cumming, 1935 (Box Box 8)
      - Correspondence of Hugh Smith Cumming, 1936-1939 (Box Box 8)
      - Correspondence of Hugh Smith Cumming, 1940 January to June (Box Box 8)
      - Correspondence of Hugh Smith Cumming, 1940 July to December (Box Box 8)
      - Correspondence of Hugh Smith Cumming, 1941 January to August (Box Box 8)
      - Correspondence of Hugh Smith Cumming, 1941 Sep-Dec (Box Box 8)
      - Correspondence of Hugh Smith Cumming, 1941-1948 (Box Box 8)
      - Correspondence of Hugh Smith Cumming, 1942-1948 (Box Box 9)
      - Correspondence of Hugh Smith Cumming, 1949, 1959-1973 (Box Box 9)
    - B: Chronological Files
      - Chronological File, 1957 May 6-1959 June (Box Box 9)
      - Chronological File, 1959 July-1961 Apr 22 (Box Box 9)
      - Chronological File, 1962 Feb 24-1963 Dec 16 (Box Box 9)
      - Chronological File, 1964-1965 (Box Box 9)
      - Chronological File, 1966-1969 (Box Box 10)
      - Chronological File, 1970-1979 (Box Box 10)
    - C: Alphabetical Files
      - Correspondence: A-B, 1943-1950 (Box Box 10)
      - Correspondence: C-D, 1932 and 1943-1949 (Box Box 10)
      - Correspondence: E-F, 1942-1950 (Box Box 10)
      - Correspondence: G, 1943-1947 (Box Box 10)
      - Correspondence: J, 1943-1947 (Box Box 10)
      - Correspondence: K-L, Mc and N, 1943-1947 (Box Box 11)
      - Correspondence: A-C, 1959-1960 (Box Box 11)
      - Correspondence: D-L, 1959-1960 (Box Box 11)
      - Correspondence: M-Z, 1959-1960 (Box Box 11)
      - Correspondence: A-B, 1960-1977 (Box Box 11)
      - Correspondence: C, 1953 and 1961-1977 (Box Box 11)
      - Correspondence: D-F, 1961-1976 (Box Box 12)
      - Correspondence: G-H, 1961-1976 (Box Box 12)
      - Correspondence: I-K, 1957 and 1961-1977 (Box Box 12)
      - Correspondence: L-M, 1961-1975 (Box Box 12)
      - Correspondence: N-Q, 1961-1978 (Box Box 12)
      - Correspondence: R-S, 1961-1979 (Box Box 12)
      - Correspondence: T-V, 1961-1979 (Box Box 13)
      - Correspondence: W-Z, 1961-1977 (Box Box 13)
    - D: Topical Files
      - Letters of Winifred B. Cumming to her family, 1930-1932 and 1951-1952 (Box Box 13)
      - Letters of Mr. and Mrs. Cordell Hull to Hugh Smith Cumming, Jr., 1933-1946, 1950 (Box Box 13)
      - Letters to Hugh Smith Cumming, Jr. from Members of Congress and government officials, 1947-1950 (Box Box 13)
      - Condolence Letters and related items re the death of Hugh S. Cumming, Sr., 1948-1949 (Box Box 13)
      - Letters of Hugh S. and Winifred Cumming to Lucy Booth Cumming, 1948-1952 (Box Box 13)
      - Letters of Hugh S. and Winifred Cumming to Lucy Booth Cumming, 1953-1954 (Box Box 13)
      - Letters of Hugh S. and Winifred Cumming to Lucy Booth Cumming, 1955-1957 (Box Box 14)
      - Condolence Letters re the death of Lucy Booth Cumming(Folder 1 of 2), 1960 (Box Box 14)
      - Condolence Letters re the death of Lucy Booth Cumming(Folder 2 of 2), 1960 (Box Box 14)
    - E: Subject Files
      - Alibi Club(Folder 1 of 3), 1937, 1959-1968 (Box Box 14)
      - Alibi Club(Folder 2 of 3), 1969-1974 (Box Box 14)
      - Alibi Club(Folder 3 of 3), 1976-1984 (Box Box 14)
      - Anderson and Sheppard, Ltd., 1957-1963 (Box Box 14)
      - Appointments and Efficiency Ratings, 1929-1947 (Box Box 14)
      - Atlantic Council, 1962-1972 (Box Box 15)
      - Bath County Community Hospital(Folder 1 of 2), 1964-1968 (Box Box 15)
      - Bath County Community Hospital(Folder 2 of 2), 1969-1977 (Box Box 15)
      - Berkshire Farm For Boys (Washington Committee), 1961 (Box Box 15)
      - Board of Examiners of Foreign Service, 1957-1960 (Box Box 15)
      - Frederick Bunnell-Vassar College, 1973-1974 (Box Box 15)
      - Chevy Chase Club, 1934, 1943-1947 (Box Box 15)
      - Christ Church(Georgetown), 1975 (Box Box 15)
      - Cosmos Club, 1961-1967 (Box Box 15)
      - Churches, 1955-1964 (Box Box 15)
      - City Tavern, 1960-1966 (Box Box 15)
      - Conference: The United States Ambassador; University of Pennsylvania, 1963 (Box Box 15)
      - Cumming Family, 1962-1969, 1975 (Box Box 15)
      - Mrs. Hugh Smith Cumming, Sr., 1951-1960 (Box Box 16)
      - Hugh Smith Cumming Trust(Folder 1 of 2), 1950-1967 (Box Box 16)
      - Hugh Smith Cumming Trust(Folder 2 of 2), 1968-1979 (Box Box 16)
      - Hugh S. and Lucy Booth Cumming Memorial Fund, 1965-1975 (Box Box 16)
      - Estate of Lucy Booth Cumming, 1962-1964 (Box Box 16)
      - Diplomatic and Consular Officers, Retired(DACOR), 1959-1968 (Box Box 16)
      - Davidson College, 1978 (Box Box 16)
      - Thomas N. Downing, 1960-1961 (Box Box 16)
      - John Foster Dulles: Princeton University Oral History Project(Folder 1 of 2), 1963-1965 (Box Box 16)
      - John Foster Dulles: Princeton University Oral History Project(Folder 2 of 2), 1966-1970 (Box Box 16)
      - Family and Child Service: Episcopal Diocese and Research Committees, 1960-1962 (Box Box 16)
      - Financial Papers: Miscellaneous diplomatic and personal, 1937 and 1941-1950 (Box Box 17)
      - Foreign Service Advisory Committee, 1960 (Box Box 17)
      - Foxcroft School, 1978-1979 (Box Box 17)
      - Garth Newel Music Center, Hot Springs, Virginia, 1979 (Box Box 17)
      - Nell Hayne, 1975-1976 (Box Box 17)
      - Historic Georgetown, Inc., 1965-1979 (Box Box 17)
      - Culver Gleysteen, 1971-1972 (Box Box 17)
      - Kendrick Family, 1964-1978 (Box Box 17)
      - John B. Kendrick, II, 1976-1978 (Box Box 17)
      - Margaret Kendrick, 1976-1978 (Box Box 17)
      - Anthony Lake, 1961-1962 (Box Box 17)
      - Meridan House Foundation, 1963-1971 (Box Box 17)
      - Metropolitan Club(Folder 1 of 2), 1934, 1943-1962 (Box Box 17)
      - Metropolitan Club(Folder 2 of 2), 1963-1972 (Box Box 18)
      - Miscellaneous, 1957, 1962, 1972-1979 (Box Box 18)
      - Sir Oscar Morland, 1973-1977 (Box Box 18)
      - Moscow Church, 1952-1962 (Box Box 18)
      - Moscow Transfer, 1950 (Box Box 18)
      - Rev. H. R. Mumford, 1975-1977 (Box Box 18)
      - National Cathedral Association(Folder 1 of 2), 1961-1964 (Box Box 18)
      - National Cathedral Association(Folder 2 of 2), 1964 May-1978 (Box Box 18)
      - The Raven Society, 1959-1960 (Box Box 18)
      - Marjorie Savage, 1961 (Box Box 18)
      - State Department--personnel actions, etc, 1948-1969 (Box Box 18)
      - Stockholm, Sweden--vouchers and items re related activities, 1945-1950 (Box Box 18)
      - Stockholm, Sweden--miscellaneous correspondence, 1948-1950 (Box Box 18)
      - Swannanoa Lots, 1932 and 1961-1966 (Box Box 18)
      - United States Navy: East Indies, 1957 (Box Box 19)
      - University of the Pacific-- Stockton, 1977-1978 (Box Box 19)
      - University of Virginia(Folder 1 of 2), 1961-1972 (Box Box 19)
      - University of Virginia(Folder 2 of 2), 1975-1978 (Box Box 19)
      - Virginia Historical Society, 1962-1963 and 1971 (Box Box 19)
      - Virginia Military Institute: 40th Class Reunion, 1961 (Box Box 19)
      - Virginia Military Institute: military items, 1917-1920 and 1971 (Box Box 19)
      - Washington Institute of Foreign Affairs, 1961-1968 (Box Box 19)
      - West Family, 1960-1968 (Box Box 19)
      - Wise Family, 1960-1971 (Box Box 19)
      - Birne T. West, 1968-1972 (Box Box 19)
      - Birne T. West Trust, 1967-1972 (Box Box 20)
      - Frank A. West, 1962-1968 (Box Box 20)
      - Woodrow Wilson House Council, 1964-1972 (Box Box 20)
  - Series II. Photographs and Miscellaneous
    - Photographs, 1918, 1923, 1943 and 1945, ca. 1964, n.d. (Box Box 20)
    - Photographs: U.S. Guard Coast in Greenland during World War II with a published article by Hugh Smith Cumming, Jr. re the U.S. Antarctic Service, and also photographs of U. S. S. Bear of the U. S. Antartic Service, 1939-1941 (Box Box 20)
    - Official Photographs of Hugh Smith Cumming, Jr., 1939, 1944-1961 (Box Box 20)
    - Photographs re activities of Hugh Smith Cumming, Jr. in Reykjavik, Iceland, 1946-1947 (Box Box 20)
    - Photographs of Richard M. Nixon in Indonesia during his Asian Tour, ca. 1953 (Box Box 20)
    - Newspaper Clippings, 1861, 1933-1963 (Box Box 20)
    - Passports of Hugh S. and Winifred B. Cumming, 1922-1947 (Box Box 20)
    - Miscellaneous Items, 1909 and 1913-1966 (Box Box 21)
    - Invitations, 1931-1964 (Box Box 21)
    - Banner, University of Virginia O.W.L.S. Society, 1959-1960 (Box Box 21)
    - West Family Genealogical Material, n.d. (Box Box 21)
  - Series III. Bound Volumes
    - Diary and Commonplace Book of Diana Whiting Smith Cumming, 1866-1868 (Box Box 22)
    - Diary of visit to a Miss Marion Kemp in New York City, 1892 April 7-29 (Box Box 23)
    - Diary of Hugh Smith Cumming, Jr.'s trip to Greenland, 1941 April 6-June 6 (Box Box 23)
    - Typescript copy of Hugh Smith Cumming, Jr.'s diary re his trip to Greenland on the Coast Guard Cutter Northland and his return home at the time of the battle between the Hood and the Bismarck, 1941 April 6-June 6 (Box Box 23)
    - Papers re Hugh Smith Cumming, Jr.'s voyage on the U. S. Coast Guard cutter Northland: Greenland trip, 1941 (Box Box 23)
    - Tapes, T 842; 1 five-inch reel, 7.5 ips
      A) 5 December 1969 [Telephone] interview of Ambassador Cumming by [Bob Wilson] broadcast over KWYO, Sheridan, Wyoming. Discusses his diplomatic service in China, Russia, Indonesia, and Sweden. 5 minutes.
      B) ca. 1951. Series of satirical songs, recorded at the American embassy in Moscow during the Korean War, when embassy personnel were restricted to the grounds and entertainment was scarce. 30 minutes.